Finding Aid for Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund Records 1929-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund Records 1929-1950, 1934-1940
Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund.
1 oversize volumes
14 linear feet
The last will and testament of Horace H. Rackham provided for the establishment of a trust fund to provide for the health and welfare of individuals, particularly the sick, aged, the young, the poor, and other underprivileged. Much of the trust money went to the University of Michigan to be used for a building for the graduate school and an endowment to be used for different kinds of research. The Fund also awarded grants to agencies involved in child welfare, community culture, education, health, philanthropy, and science. The Fund distributed money from 1934 until about 1941. The series in this record group consist of administrative and executive files, and project applications and grant files.
851587 Bs 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred to the library from the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies in 1967. (Donor no. 972 )
The record group is open for research.
The Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund was the agency created in 1934 to administer the terms of the trust created by the last will and testament of Horace H. Rackham. Under Article II of the articles of incorporation, the Fund was to "effectually carry out and administer the benevolent, charitable, educational, and scientific trust created by Horace H. Rackham to promote the health, welfare, happiness, education, training, and development of men, women and children, particularly the sick, aged, young, erring, poor, crippled, helpless, handicapped, unfortunate and under-privileged, regardless of race, in the world ...."
Accordingly, the trustees of the Fund, working conscientiously over the next six years to fulfill the terms of the trust, funded an extraordinary number of projects that they believed Rackham himself would have supported. In practice, their support divides into three areas: charity and benevolence, education, and science.
The estate which the Fund was to administer was estimated at around 10 million dollars. The trustees and officers of the Fund were Mrs. Mary A. Rackham (honorary president), Bryson D. Horton (chairman and treasurer), Arthur J. Lacy (president), Mrs. Myra H. Bussey (vice-president), Clarence E. Wilcox (secretary), and Dr. Mark S. Knapp (director). Lacy's term as president was cut short when he decided to become a candidate for governor in 1935. Mrs. Rackham was anxious about the publicity that might accrue to the Fund because of Lacy's candidacy and requested his resignation. He was succeeded as president by Frederick Rolland.
The work of investigating potential areas and recipients of support and distributing money was handled out of an Ann Arbor office which the Fund referred to as the executive office. All programs of course had to be approved by the five trustees. The director's office was originally located in the Nickels Arcade, but later moved in 1936 to a room in Angell Hall, a building at the University of Michigan, and then to the Rackham Building following its completion. Within the executive office, the Fund's director administered daily operations, undertook investigations of prospective recipients, and communicated back to the Fund's trustees. The fund's first director, Dr. Mark Knapp, resigned in 1936 and was succeeded by Mrs. Mary Clark. Knapp's area of specialty was medical research. His successor, Clark was a tireless worker who seemed to have a close relationship to Mrs. Rackham based upon the frequency of their correspondence.
The administrative offices of the Fund were located in Detroit in the Dime Bank Building. Here Bryson D. Horton who had assumed the office of Fund secretary dealt with financial problems pertaining to the administration of the Rackham estate, probate matters, and related issues. The Rackham estate was large and complicated and Horton was continually dealing with matters of bonds, property, and other investments. The Fund secretary also counseled the Ann Arbor office on problems relating to the distribution of funds.
There were many recipients of the Rackham estate but without question the biggest beneficiary was the University of Michigan. During his lifetime, Horace H. Rackham was a generous donor to the university. With his passing, President Ruthven and other university officials opened negotiations with the trustees of the Rackham Fund arguing that a major gift to the university would fulfill Horace Rackham's wish that his wealth be used for research and educational purposes. President Ruthven proposed a gift of $5 million dollars to be used for the building and endowment of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. In 1935, the trustees agreed to the proposal, and in fact added 1.5 million to the 1 million originally suggested for the construction of the Rackham Building. In the next five years, the Fund or Mary Rackham personally donated funding for different university projects, principally a 1 million dollar gift in 1936 from Mary Rackham to establish the Institute for Human Adjustment and another million in 1937 from the Fund to establish the Rackham Arthritis Research Fund. In all from 1935 to 1936, the Rackham Fund and Mary Rackham personally gave nearly $12 million dollars to the University of Michigan.
Beyond the gifts to the university, the Fund also awarded grants to numerous other worthwhile agencies. For purposes of analysis, these gifts divide into six groups: child welfare, community culture, education, health, philanthropy, and science. The following is a list of specific organizations (including University of Michigan).
Child Welfare
Boytown
Bay Cliff Health Camp
University of Michigan Fresh Air Camp
Shady Trails
Boys Club of Detroit
Starr Commonwealth for Boys
Williams House (Detroit)
Franklin Settlement
Sophie Wright Settlement
Protestant Children's Home
German Protestant Home for Orphans and Old People
Detroit Industrial School
Michigan Children's Aid Society
Community Culture
Fenton Community Center
Horace H. Rackham Memorial Fountain (at the Zoo)
Education
Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies (University of Michigan building and endowment)
University of Michigan Institute for Human Adjustment; includes:
Speech Clinic
Psychological Clinic
Sociological Research Project (Flint)
Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial (Detroit)
Horace H. Rackham School of Special Education (EMU)
Archaeology in Egypt
Health
University of Michigan Rackham Arthritis Research Unit
Michigan Society for Mental Hygiene
Philanthropy and Other Welfare
Arnold Home for the Aged and Incurables, Detroit
King's Daughter and Sons Home for Aged People, Detroit
Detroit Baptist Missionary Society
Science
Agriculture research (MSU)
Studies in biological and zoological research and crystallization of metals under stress and strain (Albion College)
Atomic nuclear research (U-M)
In addition to these public gifts, one account of the Fund was used for direct relief to individuals, mainly Rackham family members needing some assistance. Each month, this B.R. account (for blood relation) would dispense some $1600 to 50 or so individuals. Sometimes the disbursements would go up or down depending on changed conditions. The size of the monthly checks ranged from $25 to $50. Most of these cash payments were in fact a continuation of assistance that Rackham had made during his lifetime.
The personal relief effort of Mary Rackham was not publicized for obvious reasons. Every year Fund offices received many hundreds of letters asking for individual assistance or aid to charitable organizations. The great bulk of these were rejected for reason of being out-of-state, out of the Fund's scope of activities, made on behalf of organizations not yet established, or because they sought some form of personal relief.
By 1941, virtually the entire Fund had been disbursed, and in December 1942, the trustees filed a certificate of dissolution. By law a period of three years must elapse before the corporation could be dissolved. In point of fact, the Fund continued to receive statements of assets and liabilities up to 1950.
Further information about the Fund will be found in the following works.
Baker, Sheridan W., Jr. The Rackham Funds of the University of Michigan 1933-1953. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, 1955.
Brazer, Marjorie Cahn. Biography of an Endowment; The Horace H. Rackham Fund at the University of Michigan. Rackham Board of Governors, 1985.
Miner, Frances H., ed. Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund; Detroit and Ann Arbor 1934-1940. Ann Arbor: Published by the Trustees, 1940.
The records of the Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund document the continuing generosity of Horace Rackham and Mary Rackham to numerous charitable, educational, and scientific organizations and causes. The records contain the files of the Fund's trustees and directors and provide insight and information about such topics as the administration of a philanthropic fund-giving organization during the mid-1930s, the kinds of gifts made, the relationship among the Fund's trustees and officers, and the relationship between the Fund and the grant recipients. Because of the size of the gift, most of the documentation within the record group details the close ties between the Fund and the University of Michigan. These files concern not only the establishment of the Rackham endowment to the University, but also the different scientific and educational grants made. Additionally, these files detail the construction of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies building in Ann Arbor and the Rackham Educational Memorial building in Detroit.
The records of the Fund cover the period of 1929-1950 though they bulk largest for the period of the Fund's greatest activity, 1934-1940. The record group has been separated into two series: Combined Administrative and Executive Office Files and Project applications/grants.
Subjects:
Adrian College (Adrian, Mich.); Aged--Michigan.; Albion College.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Archaeological expeditions--Egypt.; Arnold Home, Inc.; Bay Cliff Health Camp.; Birth control.; Boy Scouts of America.; Boytown Camp (Washtenaw County, Mich.); Boys Club of Detroit (Mich.); Child welfare--Michigan.; Children's Fund of Michigan.; Clark, Mary H.; Depressions--1929--United States.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit Baptist Missionary Society.; Detroit Zoological Park (Mich.); Michigan State Normal College.; Fenton (Mich.); Fenton Community Center.; Ferris Institute.; Flint (Mich.); Flint Institute of Research and Planning.; Flushing (Mich.); Franklin Settlement Summer Camp (Lake Orion, Mich.); Fresh Air Camp (University of Michigan); German Protestant Home for Orphans and Old People (Detroit, Mich.); Goodwill Industries of America.; Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund.; Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial (Detroit, Mich.); Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Kalamazoo College.; King's Daughters and Sons Home for Aged People.; Mason (Mich.); Maternal Health League of Michigan.; Methodist Children's Home Society of Michigan.; Michigan Children's Aid Society.; Michigan Society for Mental Health.; Michigan State University.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; National Urban League.; Oakland County (Mich.); Olivet College.; Philanthropists--Michigan.; Pontiac (Mich.); Port Huron (Mich.); Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (University of Michigan); Shady Trails Camp (Northport, Mich.); Sophie Wright Settlement.; Spring Arbor College (Spring Arbor, Mich.); Starr Commonwealth for Boys.; University of Chicago.; University of Michigan--Benefactors.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Endowments.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--Funds and scholarships.; University of Michigan. Institute for Human Adjustment.; University of Michigan--Students--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; University of Michigan--Trust funds.; W. K. Kellogg Foundation.; Williams House, Inc.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)
Contributors:
Horton, Bryson Dexter, 1871-1945.; Knapp, Mark Stevens, 1872-1948.; Novy, Frederick George, 1864-1957.; Rackham, Horace H., 1858-1933.; Rackham, Mary A. Horton, d. 1947.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Bay Cliff Health Camp.; Boytown Camp (Washtenaw County, Mich.); Camps--Michigan.; Children playing.; Detroit Zoological Park (Mich.); Fountains--Michigan--Detroit.; Franklin Settlement Summer Camp (Lake Orion, Mich.); Fountains--Design and construction.; Fenton (Mich.); Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund.
- Combined Administrative and Executive Office Files 1933-1950
  The series titled Combined Administrative and Executive Office Files (1933-1950; 4 linear feet) is an amalgam of records received and combined from the Detroit offices of Fund trustees and the Ann Arbor offices of the Fund directors. How these records came together is not clear. Probably after the Fund dissolved, the Detroit records were transferred to Ann Arbor to be stored with the executive office files in the Rackham Building, and with movement the distinction between the files was lost. This series provides the clearest overview of the work of the Fund, especially through the minutes of the trustees and the director's reports. The chronological files have value for their insight into the relationship between the trustees and the director in Ann Arbor, who, with his/her staff, prepared the reports, made the recommendations, and acted as buffer between the trustees and those seeking funds. A significant portion of this series pertains to the relationship with University of Michigan administrators and faculty over the different grants made. The different building projects underwritten by the Fund are documented in this series. There are also financial records indicating the size and complexity of the Fund's operation.
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees minutes 1934-1940, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Director's reports 1934-January 1936, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Report, to trustees by Mary H. Clark entitled, "The Problem of Old Age Relief," 1935 (Box 1)
  - Report 1937 (Box 1)
  - Report, "Final distribution of funds," 1940 (Box 1)
  - Statistical information, applications accepted/applications rejected (Box 1)
  - Chronological, mainly files of Bryson Horton, Mark Knapp, and Mary Clark 1934-1948, 34 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Grants and Endowments (Box 2)
    - General
      - Chronological, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Legal documents 1936 (Box 2)
      - Tax problems (Box 2)
      - Undergraduate scholarships, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Medical research
      - Arthritis study (Box 2)
      - Brain psychology (Box 2)
      - Cancer of the eye, Dr. L. Lane (Box 2)
      - Chidester, Dr. F.E (Box 2)
      - Dental carries (Box 2)
      - Expectant mothers (Box 2)
      - Heart station (Box 2)
      - Infantile paralysis (Box 2)
      - Metabolism research (Box 2)
      - Post graduate medicine (Box 2)
      - Ratner, Dr. Herbert (Box 2)
      - Rickets research (Box 2)
      - Syphilis (Box 2)
      - Therapeutic pool (Box 2)
      - Visual acuity (Box 2)
      - Water balance, thyroid (Box 2)
    - Other research/projects
      - Archaeological, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Astronomy, South Africa (Box 2)
      - Delinquent children (Box 2)
      - Fresh Air Camp (Box 2)
      - Freshmen College (Box 2)
      - Institute for Human Adjustment
        - General (Box 2)
        - Psychological Clinic (Box 2)
        - Speech Clinic (Box 2)
      - McMath-Hulbert Observatory (Box 2)
      - Physics research (Box 2)
      - Psychology, Study in student thinking (Box 2)
      - Research fellowship (Box 2)
      - Social work training (Box 2)
    - Rackham Building (.3 linear ft.) (Box 3)
    - Rackham Educational Memorial/Rackham Engineering Foundation (.3 linear ft.) (Box 3)
  - Rackham estate documents (.3 linear ft.) (Box 3)
  - Auditor's reports 1936-1940, 8 volumes (Box 4)
  - Financial reports and statements (Box 4)
  - Assets and liabilities, monthly statements 1938-1950, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Clippings 1933-1938, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1934-1938 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1938-1942 (Volume 1)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
- Project applications/grants 1934-1942
  The series Project applications/grants (1934-1940; 10 linear feet) is an alphabetical series of correspondence, reports, grant proposals, and other materials from those groups and individuals seeking money. Though many of these individual files are slight containing only a letter requesting funds and a form response from the Fund director, this series contains the records of the agencies that were successful in obtaining money for their projects. These files are fuller and document the continuing relationship between the Fund and the recipient of a grant. These files document some of the accomplishments of the Fund and the impact it made in different communities within the state and on individual lives. A key to these fuller files may be found on pp. ii-iii of this finding aid. Except for the University of Michigan grants, documentation about each of the organizations listed on those pages will be found in the Project applications/grants series.
  - A miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Adrian College (Box 5)
  - Adult education, Bruce (Box 5)
  - Affiliated Schools for Workers (Box 5)
  - Albion College (Box 5)
  - Albion College, Carter (Box 5)
  - Albion College, Chickering (Box 5)
  - Albion College, Prescott (Box 5)
  - Albion College, Scientific research (Box 5)
  - Albion College, X-ray equipment (Box 5)
  - All Saints Episcopal Hospital, Fort Worth (Box 5)
  - Allied Youth, Detroit (Box 5)
  - Allied Youth for Prohibition (Box 5)
  - Alma College (Box 5)
  - Alphadelphian Academy (Box 5)
  - Alumnae Association College City of Detroit (Box 5)
  - Alumni Association, University of Michigan (Box 5)
  - A.M.E. Community Church, Grand Rapids (Box 5)
  - Amateur Chemists Society, Lansing (Box 5)
  - American Academy of Tropical Medicine (Box 5)
  - American Association for Social Security (Box 5)
  - American Association of Medical Social Workers (Box 5)
  - American Association to Promote the Teaching of Speech to the Deaf (Box 5)
  - American Bar Association (Box 5)
  - American Camping Association, Twining (Box 5)
  - American Choral and Festival Alliance, Inc., Boston (Box 5)
  - American Christian Committee for German Refugees (Box 5)
  - American Committee on Economic Policy (Box 5)
  - American Council on Education (Box 5)
  - American Farm School, Salonica, Greece (Box 5)
  - American Federation of Arts (Box 5)
  - American Federation of Organizations for the Hard of Hearing, Inc (Box 5)
  - American Foundation for the Blind (Box 5)
  - American Game Association (Box 5)
  - American Humane Education Society (Box 5)
  - American Legion, Child Welfare Committee (Box 5)
  - American Legion, Indian Social Plan (Box 5)
  - American Merchant Marine Library Association (Box 5)
  - American Otological Society (Box 5)
  - American Red Cross (Box 5)
  - American Red Cross, Flood Relief Fund (Box 5)
  - American Sociological Society (Box 5)
  - American University, Beirut (Box 5)
  - American Youth Hostels, Inc., Northfield, Mass (Box 5)
  - Anderson, Mrs. C.C (Box 5)
  - Andrews, Mrs. Friend (Box 5)
  - Angell, Lillian (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Child's Service Bureau (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Community Forum (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Community Fund (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor League, for hard of hearing (Box 5)
  - Antioch College (Box 5)
  - Appleyard, Mrs. Bertha (Box 5)
  - Arnold Home (Box 5)
  - Art Center Music School, Detroit (Box 5)
  - Asbury College (Box 5)
  - Association of American Colleges (Box 5)
  - Assumption Parish Health Unit, Napoleonville, La (Box 5)
  - Asthma Research Council (Box 5)
  - Atlanta School of Social Work (Box 5)
  - Augustian Mission Helpers (Box 5)
  - B miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Babcock School for Retarded Children, Detroit (Box 5)
  - Bahm, Archie, U-M Dept. of Philosophy (Box 5)
  - Bangs, Kate (Box 5)
  - Baptist Children's Home, Detroit Baptist Union (Box 5)
  - Barnes, Donald J (Box 5)
  - Barton, Mrs. E.J (Box 5)
  - Bates, Henry M., U-M Law School (Box 5)
  - Bathurst, Effie, Teachers College, Columbia University (Box 5)
  - Bauer, Walter, Massachusetts General Hospital (Box 5)
  - Bay Cliff Health Camp (Box 5)
    (includes photos)
  - Berea College (Box 5)
  - Berger, E.E (Box 5)
  - Bethel Home for the Aged, Framingham, Mass (Box 5)
  - Better Homes in America (Box 5)
  - Beverly Hills Hospital Association, Dibble (Box 5)
  - Biethan, Sue, U-M Medical Library (Box 5)
  - Birth Control League of Michigan (Box 5)
  - Birth Control, Margaret Sanger (Box 5)
  - Blackman, Mrs. Daisy (Box 6)
  - Blake, Mrs. Michael (Box 6)
  - Blind (Box 6)
  - Board of Education, Fenton, Mich (Box 6)
  - Boll, Helen (Box 6)
  - Booker Washington Association, Montgomery, Ala. (Box 6)
  - Booth Community Hospital and Old Folks Home (Box 6)
  - Boston University (Box 6)
  - Bouslog, Carl (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts of America, Detroit Council (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts of America, Monroe County (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts of America, St. Clair Council (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts of America, Washtenaw-Livingston Council (Box 6)
  - Boys Club, Detroit, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Boytown Camp, 2 folders (Box 6)
    (includes photographs)
  - Branch County Community Corporation (Box 6)
  - Breitmeyer, Philip, Christian Science Sanitorium, Clarkston, Mich (Box 6)
  - Bryn Mawr College (Box 6)
  - Budge, Allene (Box 6)
  - Bushman property (Box 6)
  - Bussey, Mrs. C.L (Box 6)
  - Busy Bee Home Society (Box 6)
  - Butterfield, Walter Scott (Box 6)
  - C miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Calhoun Colored School, Calhoun, Lowndes County, Ala (Box 6)
  - Camlin, William J (Box 6)
  - Camp Directors Association of America, Inc (Box 6)
  - Camp Fire Girls (Box 6)
  - Camp Lakeside, Detroit District of the Evangelical Church (Box 6)
  - Camp Margaret Murray Washington (Box 6)
  - Camp Ohiyesa, YMCA, Detroit (Box 6)
  - Campbell (John C.) Folk School (Box 6)
  - Camps miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Canadian Bureau for the Advancement of Music (Box 6)
  - Carnegie (Box 6)
  - Caspian Community Center (Box 6)
  - Central College, Iowa (Box 6)
  - Central Hanover Bank and Trust Company (Box 6)
  - Chapin, Olive (Box 6)
  - Charleton, A.J (Box 6)
  - Chesnut, Mrs. Elizabeth (Box 6)
  - Child Welfare League of America, Inc (Box 6)
  - Children's Center, Watson (Box 6)
  - Children's Fund of Michigan (Box 6)
  - Children's Home Society of Florida (Box 6)
  - Children's Hospital of Boston (Box 6)
  - Children's Hospital of Michigan (Box 6)
  - Children's Vacation Farm (Box 6)
  - Christ Church Social Service Department (Box 6)
  - Christian Medical Association of India (Box 6)
  - Christian Science Benevolent Association (Box 6)
  - Chung Mei Home for Chinese Voters (Box 6)
  - Church of Christ, Beulah Free Circulating Library (Box 6)
  - Citizen's Housing and Planning Council, Detroit (Box 6)
  - Citizen's Medical Reference Bureau (Box 6)
  - Civic Pride Association of Greater Detroit (Box 6)
  - Clear Creek Mountain Springs School (Box 6)
  - Cleveland Foundation (Box 6)
  - Clifford, Gordon (Box 6)
  - Clippenger, Louis (Box 6)
  - Coffman, H.C (Box 6)
  - Colgate University (Box 6)
  - Columbia University (Box 6)
  - Committee for the Study of Sex Variants, Inc (Box 6)
  - Committee on Care and Training of Delinquent Girls, National Committee on Prison and Labor (Box 6)
  - Committee on County Reorganization in Michigan (Box 6)
  - Committee on Friendly Relations among Foreign Students (Box 6)